Personal Papers of Elmer Ellsworth Brown: 1827-1936 MC 16
New York University Archives
- Series VI. PERSONAL AND PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS 1869-1911 (Boxes 19-23)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1897 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1898 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1899 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1900 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1901 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1902 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1903 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1904 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1905 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Department of Pedagogy: Student Enrollment, Class Reports, Miscellaneous Reports (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Notebook for Courses, "Theory of Education" and "School Systems", 1897 1899 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Oakland Public School Reports; Alameda County Teachers' Institute, 1892-1896 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Department of Pedagogy: Printed Material, 1892-1903 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - California, University of: General University Printed Material (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1906 July-1906 Dec. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Letter Book (outgoing), 1906-1907 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1907 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Letter Book (outgoing), 1907-1908 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1908 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Letter Book (outgoing), 1908 Apr.-1908 Oct. (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1909 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1910 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1911 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - New York University (Chancellor): Correspondence, 1911 July-1911 Dec. (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Series VII. PRE-RETIREMENT AWARDS AND TRIBUTES 1905-1933 (Box 24)
  The bulk of this material relates to various awards and tributes bestowed upon Brown for his service as educator and particularly, for his leadership of New York University. Included are congratulatory letters for twenty years of service in 1931, and his receipt of the Commendatore of the Order of the Crown of Italy in 1932, and the Order of the Crown of Belgium in 1933.
  - Louisiana Purchase Exposition Company: International Exposition of Industry and Labor, 1905-1906 1913 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - New York University Law School Alumni Association: Annual Banquet, 1912 Mar. (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Testimonial Dinner Honoring EEB on Fifteen Years of Service at N.Y.U. November 8, 1926, 1926 Oct.-1926 Dec. (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - LL.D. Degree Conferred by the University of the State of New York, October 16, 1930, 1930 Oct.-1930 Dec. (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Letters of Congratulations on Twenty Years of Service at N.Y.U., 1931 Nov.-1931 Dec. (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Letters of Congratulations on Twenty Years of Service at N.Y.U., 1931 Nov.-1931 Dec. (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Commendatore of the Order of the Crown of Italy, March 24, 1932, 1932 Mar.-1932 May (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Order of the Crown of Belgium, April 11, 1933, 1933 Apr.-1933 May (Box 24, Folder 8)
- Series VIII. RETIREMENT 1932-1935 (Boxes 24-26)
  These files include announcements of Brown's retirement from the chancellorship of New York University, reactions and responses from friends and colleagues, material relating to a retirement dinner held in his honor on May 3, 1933, correspondence concerning his illness, the establishment of the Brown House for English studies on the University Heights campus of NYU, and papers relating to his European trip taken shortly before his death in 1934.
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Response from Friends, Colleagues, and Organizations includes reaction to selection of Harry W. Chase as EEB's successor), 1932-1933 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Retirement Dinner, May 3, 1933: Programs, Speeches, Clippings, 1933 Jan.-1933 July (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Retirement Dinner, May 3, 1933: Testimonial Book with Signatures, 1933 May 3 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Retirement Dinner, May 3, 1933: Correspondence, 1933 Apr.-1933 May (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Retirement Dinner, May 3, 1933: Correspondence, 1933 May (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, including references to final illness, 1933 May-1933 Dec. (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, including references to final illness, 1934-1935 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Award of the Legion d'honneur, August 12, 1933, 1933-1935 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Brown House for English Studies: Letter to Finley J. Shephard and Newspaper Clipping, 1933-1934 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - European Trip, January 21 to April 3, 1934, 1933-1934 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Browning, Edward W.: Will re: Browning Prize, 1934 Oct. (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Series IX. OBITUARIES, FUNERAL ARRANGEMENTS, AND MEMORIAL SERVICE 1932-1935 (Boxes 26-27)
  These files include announcements of Elmer E. Brown's death, funeral arrangements, a memorial service held on January 17, 1935, and Brown's personal effects, which include insurance policies, calling cards, passport, and various clippings.
  - Announcements, Obituaries, Funeral Arrangements, Acknowledgments, 1934 Nov. (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Memorial Service, January 17, 1935 and Post-Death Tributes, 1934-1935 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Memorial Book and Letters of Acknowledgment, 1935 Mar.-1935 Dec. (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Personal Effects: check stubs, Corn Exchange Bank Trust Co.; abridgment of Murray's English Grammar... (1823); wallet containing calling cards, clippings, and hotel credit cards; miscellaneous quotations; passport; fire insurance policy; photograph of Fanny Brown; typescript of prayer; Bible alphabet. (Box 27, Folder 1)
- Series X. ESTATE PAPERS 1932-1936 (Boxes 27-28)
  The Brown estate papers include a copy of his will, an insurance policy, legal correspondence regarding stock holdings, income tax papers, miscellaneous vouchers, canceled checks and bank statements, distribution of bequests, and other miscellaneous papers.
  - Will, Life Insurance Policy, 1932, 1934, 1935 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Legal Correspondence re: Stock, 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Income Tax Papers, 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Ralph Folks and David Samuels, Attorneys, 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Vouchers (miscellaneous), 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Rent Vouchers, 1934 Oct.-1934 Nov. (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Cancelled Checks and Bank Statements, 1934-1936 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Receipts and Checks (miscellaneous), 1934-1935 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Distribution of Bequests, 1934-1935 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1934-1936 (Box 28, Folder 5)